<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles for regulating of the judicatories, &amp;c. set down by the commissioners thereunto authorized by His Majesty, under the Great Seal: with His Majesties approbation thereof prefixed thereunto.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Commissioners for Regulating the Judicatories.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62412</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S999A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222486</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833653</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833653</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38131</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62412)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38131)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2177:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles for regulating of the judicatories, &amp;c. set down by the commissioners thereunto authorized by His Majesty, under the Great Seal: with His Majesties approbation thereof prefixed thereunto.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Commissioners for Regulating the Judicatories.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Evan Tyler, printer to the King's most Excellent Majesty,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  Politics and government --  1660-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38131:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ARTICLES, For Regulating of the JUDICATORIES, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Set down by the COMISSIONERS Thereunto Authorized by HIS MAJESTY, Under the GREAT SEAL: WITH His <hi>Majeſties</hi> APPROBATION thereof prefixed thereunto.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>C R</head>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
               <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms of Charles II</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINBURGH,</hi> Printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to the King's moſt Excellent MAjESTY, 1670.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:38131:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:38131:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:38131:3"/>
            <head>HIS MAJESTIES APPROBATION OF THE ARTICLES FOLLOWING.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>CHARLES R.</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HARLES,</hi> by the Grace of GOD, King of <hi>Scotland, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Faith; To all Our good Subjects whom theſe preſents do or may concern, Greeting. Wee having peruſed and conſidered the Report under-written, with the Articles, Rules and Orders made by the Commiſsioners in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s for regulating the Judicatories, and the prices of all Writs relating thereto; Wee do hereby Allow, Ratifie and Approve the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the Commiſsioners, with all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles and Orders after ſet down, and Ordain the ſame to be duly obſerved in all time coming; And for that end, that they be recorded in the <hi>Sede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt</hi>-Books of the Seſsion, and in the Books of Adjournal, and printed and publiſhed, that none
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38131:4"/>pretend ignorance thereof. And Wee do recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to Our Commiſsioners intruſted in this affair, to be careful to ſee theſe Rules and Articles punctually obſerved, and the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veeners ſeverely cenſured: As alſo, to take the whole affair into their further conſideration, that what, by the ſhortneſs of time, is not yet determined, may with all conveniency be done; And their Judgements of the remanent Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catories and whole matter, not as yet ſettled, may be returned to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, that Wee may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon give ſuch Orders, as Wee ſhall think fit.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at Our Court at <hi>Whitehal,</hi> 
                  <date>the fourth day of <hi>June,</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty, and of Our Reign the twenty two year.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By His</hi> Majeſties <hi>Command,</hi> LA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DERDAIL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="report">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:38131:4"/>
            <head>THE REPORT OF THE COMMISSIONERS APPOINTED FOR THE <hi>Regulation of the J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DICATORIES.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Edinburgh, <date>
                     <hi>2. of</hi> March, <hi>1670.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as it hath pleaſed the Kings <hi>Majeſty,</hi> by a Commiſſion under His Great-Seal, of the twenty one of <hi>September</hi> laſt, to autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize and impower ſome Noblemen and others of His Privy-Council and Seſſion, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult concerning the Judicatories of His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties</hi> Privy-Council, Seſſion, and Juſtice-Court, and the Regulating of the ſame; And for redreſſing and preventing all abuſes that are already, or may probably ariſe, or creep into the ſaids Judicatories; And to conſider the beſt, moſt ſummar and equall way of bringing in, and calling of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes for Diſpenſing of Juſtice; And for ſhortning and abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the long, chargeable, and tedious dependancy of Pleas: And to ſettle ſuch Rules and Orders as they ſhall judge neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for theſe ends, and to do every thing for making effectual His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Royal and Gracious Intention, that His Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects be relieved and ſecured againſt oppreſſion and exactions; and that Juſtice be adminiſtrate unto them with expedition, and as little trouble and charge as may be. And that the ſaids Commiſſioners return to His <hi>Majeſty</hi> an accompt in Writ of their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38131:5"/>Proceedings and Concluſion, that His <hi>Majeſty</hi> may take ſuch courſe therein, as in His Royal Wiſdom He ſhall think fit. Likeas, the Kings <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with advice and conſent of His Eſtates of Parliament, did by another Commiſſion of the twenty third of <hi>December</hi> laſt, impower the Commiſſioners above-mentioned, to conſider and regulate the Commiſſar Courts, the Sheriff-Courts, and all other inferior Courts within the Kingdom; And ſo ſet down Rules and Orders for regulating the ſame, and the Formes of proceeding therein, and the prices of all Writs, Fees and Dues to be taken any manner of way by any Perſons in, or relating to the ſaids Judicatories. In obedience to which Commiſſions, The Commiſſioners having had ſeveral meetings together, and conſulted upon the beſt and readieſt way for the proſecution of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Royal Intention, for the good and eaſe of His Subjects: And finding the ſame to be a matter of great importance, and deſerving moſt ſerious conſideration, and a longer time to make a full ſettlement therein; Yet, being deſireous, that aſſoon as is poſſible, His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Subjects may find the fruits and effects of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Royall care over them: Have at preſent agreed unto, and condeſcended upon the <hi>Rules</hi> and <hi>Articles</hi> after-following; Which they do humbly offer to His <hi>Majeſty</hi> as their Judgement, in order to the preſent Regulation of the Judicatories; Without prejudice alwayes of what upon further conſideration, they ſhall hereafter offer, for a full ſettlement therein.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:38131:5"/>
            <head>Concerning the SESSION.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eing a great part of the trouble and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences of the Liedges, in obtaining of Juſtice in their Cauſes, is occaſioned through the uncertainty of their attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance upon Proceſſes, depending before the Lords of <hi>Seſſion;</hi> Whereby not knowing any certain time, at, or about which their Proceſſes will be called: They are neceſſitat to wait on the moſt part of the time of the Seſſion, during the dependance of their Proceſſes, or otherwiſe to be abſent when the ſame are diſcuſs'd. That therefore, all Proceſſes ſhall be diſcuſſed and determined as the Parties are in readineſſe, and do call for Juſtice after the ſame have been ſeen by the Defenders Advocates, and are returned by them; And that according to the date of the Returns which are ſet down, and ſigned by the Defenders Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate upon the Proceſſe it ſelf, that no Parties be preſerred in obtaining Juſtice to any other who was ready, and calling for it before. And that Books of Enrollment be made for enrolling the ſaid Proceſſes, according to the dates of the Returns; that thereby notice may be timeouſly given to all Parties having intreſt in the Proceſſe, how far the Lords of Seſſion are advanced, in diſcuſſing and determining Proceſſes according to the ſaids Rolls, that the Parties may be preſent when their Proceſſes will fall in to be diſcuſs'd and determined, in their courſe as they ſtand in the Rolls; and may in the mean time reſt quiet and ſecure, that their Rights and Intereſts will not be decided when they cannot know to be preſent, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be attained, unleſſe all priviledges whereby any cauſe can be called, otherwiſe then according to its due courſe in the ſaids Rols, be laid aſide; Excepting only the Cauſes belonging properly to the Kings <hi>Majeſty</hi> (and not to Donators or others) which may be called at any time when his <hi>Majeſties</hi> Advocat pleaſeth, upon either of the two next <hi>Sederunt</hi>-dayes after the Proceſſe is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned; or if the ſame be not called on either of the ſaids two dayes, at any time thereafter, upon fifteen dayes advertiſement to the Defenders Advocats, that they may acquaint their Clients to be preſent.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:38131:6"/>
            <p n="2">2. That the Book of Enrollment for the Outer-houſe be kept and made up by the perſon appointed, or to be appointed by the Lords of Seſſion, who ſhall attend in the Seſſion-houſe each Saturday in Seſſion-time, from two a clock in the afternoon, till four, and ſhall take up a note of all Proceſſes ſhown to him, containing the names and deſignations of the Purſuers and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, and the name of the Cauſe, whether it be Advocation, Suſpenſion, Declarator, Reduction, or any other having a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial name; or otherwiſe under the name of Lybell'd Summonds, and contain the date of the return, ſigned by the Defenders Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocats upon the Proceſs; and by the ſaid note ſhall inſert in the Book all that is produced that day, according to the dates of the returns, expreſſing in the Book the day of the month of the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, before the Cauſes taken up that day, and alſo expreſſing the day of the month of the return, before the Cauſes returned each day, and ſhall interline nor inſert no Cauſe in the ſaid Book, but ſet them down in order as they were preſented, according to the date of their returns; and ſhall receive for inſerting of the ſaids Cauſes in the Book, and for affixing Rolls upon the Wall conform to the ſaid Book, for every Proceſs four ſhillings Scots and no more, although the ſaid Proceſs ſhould continue to be Enrolled ſeveral weeks, untill the Ordinary have called and heard the ſame; which Book of Enrollment ſhall alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the Seſſion-houſe, and be patent to the Liedges, that thence advertiſements may be given to all parties having intereſt; and for ſhewing whereof, the Keeper of the Book ſhall exact or take no money or gratification.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Keeper of the Book of Enrollment for the Outer-houſe affix a Roll of Proceſſes each Munday upon the ordinary place of the Wall of the Outer-houſe, in all things conform to the ſaid Book of Enrollment, expreſſing the day of up-taking; and that the day of the month of the ſeveral Returns be ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Proceſſes inſert each day, and each ſubſequent weeks Roll ſhall in the firſt place contain what remained undiſcuſs'd by an Act, Decreet, or Proteſtation, or not delet by the Ordinary, upon the Purſuers not inſiſting. And where Proceſſes are delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a day, till the Parties ſee, or ſomething be produced or done, which requires not an extracted Act, the ſame ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in all ſubſequent Rolls, in the ſame day that it was in the firſt Roll, that after the day to which it was delayed, it may be called by the Ordinary till it be diſcuſs'd or delet: And for that effect, the Ordinary ſhall on the Margent of the Roll, mark at that Proceſs, to what day it is delayed, which ſhall remain ſo marked in the ſubſequent Rolls, till the Cauſe be diſcuſſed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the Keeper of the ſaid Books of Enrollment for the Outer-houſe, do exactly and punctually obſerve the Rules and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38131:6"/>Orders aforeſaid, and that he give his oath every Seſſion for that effect; and if he tranſgreſs the ſaids Rules, the Lords ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive him of his Office, and otherwayes puniſh him as they ſee cauſe, and appoint another in his place, who, and his ſucceſſors, ſhall alwayes be lyable for obſerving the premiſſes.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That in like manner there be a Book of Enrollment of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes to be diſcuſs'd in the Inner-houſe, containing Cauſes proper for the Inner-houſe; as the diſcuſſing of reaſons of Reduction of Heretable Rights of Lands, or Annual-rents, Declarators of Rights thereof, Probations of Tenors of Writs deſtroyed or loſt, <hi>Ceſsiones bonorum,</hi> which Book ſhall be kept by a perſon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, or to be appointed by the Lord Chancellour, who ſhall inſert the ſaids Proceſſes as they are in readineſs to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſs'd in the Inner-houſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Reductions after the Producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is cloſed, and Declarators, Tenors, and <hi>Ceſsiones bonorum,</hi> after the Dilators are diſcuſſed in the Outer-houſe, and a great <hi>aviſandum</hi> made by the Ordinary in the Outer-houſe, who is to proceed no further therein; and that according to the date of that great <hi>aviſandum,</hi> as it ſtands written upon the Proceſs by the Clerk of the Proceſs: And where the Lords, upon report of Diſpute from the Outer-houſe made by the Ordinary, ſhall for the importance, intricacy, or preparative of the points re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, ordain the Cauſe to be heard in preſence of the whole Lords, the ſaid Proceſs ſhall be inſert in the Roll of the Inner-houſe, according to the date of the Lords deliverance, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it to be heard in their preſence.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That there be a Book of Enrollment of concluded Cauſes, whereof the probation is to be adviſed by the Lords, to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert according to the date of the concluſion of the Cauſe, as the ſame ſhall be preſented by the Clerks of the Proceſs, to be kept by the Keeper of the ſaid Book of Enrollment for the Inner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That the Keeper of the ſaids Books of Enrollment for the Inner-houſe, ſhall attend in the Seſſion-houſe each Saturday from two to three a clock in the afternoon, and ſhall receive and inſert all Proceſſes which ſhall be offered to him in either of the ſaids Books, according to the Order foreſaid; and ſhall receive thirty ſhillings Scots for each Proceſs to be inſert in the Book of Cauſes to be diſcuſs'd, and twelve ſhillings for each Cauſe to be inſert in the Book of concluded Cauſes; and ſhall exact or take no more for himſelf or his ſervants: and ſhall make the ſaids Books patent to all the Liedges freely, and ſhall affix a Roll both of Proceſſes to be diſcuſs'd in the Inner-houſe, and of concluded Cauſes, in all things conform to the Books, upon Munday, als oft as need beis; and ſhall add to the Cauſes in the ſaid Roll for ſubſequent weeks, in the ſame manner as is appointed for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38131:7"/>the Rolls of the Outer-houſe, and both in the Books and Rolls ſhall expreſs the day of up-taking the Proceſs, and the day of the great <hi>aviſandum</hi> or Ordinance of the Lords for hearing the Cauſe in their preſence, ſubjoyning thereto the Cauſes each day, both in the Books and Rolls of Cauſes to be diſcuſs'd, and the like for the Book and Roll of concluded Cauſes, according to the date of the concluſion of the Cauſe.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That the Keeper of the ſaids Books of Enrollment for the Inner-houſe obſerve the premiſſes punctually, under the pain of deprivation, and being further cenſured by the Lords, as they ſhall ſee cauſe: And that the beginning of every Seſſion, he ſhall make faith to obſerve the premiſſes in all points.</p>
            <p n="9">9. That the Lords both in the Inner-houſe and Outer-houſe ſhall proceed to the diſcuſſing of Proceſſes, in order as they ſtand in the ſaid Rolls <hi>reſpectivè,</hi> without paſſing over, or anticipating any Cauſe; and that each Proceſs ſhall be ſtill called in its order, untill it be brought to an Act, Proteſtation, or Decreet; and if it be delayed till ſomething be produced or done which requires not an Act extracted, that after the day to which it is delayed, the ſame ſhall be call'd till it be diſcuſs'd.</p>
            <p n="10">10. And where at the calling of any Cauſe in the Inner or Outer-houſe, the Purſuer inſiſts not, the Proceſs ſhall be delet out of the Roll, and Proteſtation ſhall be granted to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, without any other ſolemnity, but the demanding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of at the calling of the Cauſe, whereby the Defender ſhall not be oblidged to anſwer untill he be ſummoned of new, and the Proteſtation-money paid, that he be not oblidged to an uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain attendance at the Purſuers pleaſure. And incaſe at the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of any Proceſs in the Outer-houſe, any Parties Advocat be in the Inner-houſe, the Ordinary ſhall call the Cauſe the next day thereafter, if he be deſired upon a Ticket to be given to him before he go to the Bench; but that no Advocat make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption by calling otherwayes over the Bar.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That the Lords by no importunity alter the order of the ſaids Rolls by any Deliverance or Warrand, except it be for diſcuſſing reaſons of Reduction of ſmall difficulty and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in the Outer-houſe, before they be Enrolled in the Inner-houſe, which ſhall be Enrolled in the Roll of the Outer-houſe, according as they ſhall be preſented to the Keeper of the Roll, in the ſame manner as other Proceſſes.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That if any Cauſe be called by anticipation, out of its due place, the Purſuers Advocat may refuſe to inſiſt, or the Defenders Advocat to anſwer, and it ſhall be a ſufficient defence that he is not oblidged to anſwer before its due courſe in the Roll: And although neither parties Advocats ſhould object,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38131:7"/>ſeing others who were anterior in the Roll are prejudged, the Clerks are prohibit to write on any ſuch Proceſs called out of its own courſe, or to extract any Act or Decreet thereupon.</p>
            <p n="13">13. That the Lords of Seſſion, every Seſſion, go near the diſcuſſing of all Cauſes enrolled that Seſſion; and that as they ſee their work by the Books of enrollment, they meet the ſooner in the morning, and alſo meet in the afternoon for taking in Reports from the Outer-houſe, which requires not the attendance of Advocats, and which conſumes much of the time both in the Inner and Outer-houſe in the forenoon; and alſo for adviſing of concluded Cauſes, which of all other ſhould be leaſt delayed.</p>
            <p n="14">14. That if any Act, Decreet or Proteſtation be ſtopped, either by the Ordinary, or by the Lords, the ſame ſhall be heard by the Ordinary who heard the Cauſe before, untill the ſame be diſcuſs'd, delet, or Proteſtation granted in manner foreſaid, and that the ſame ſhall not again be brought into the Roll.</p>
            <p n="15">15. That no Bill be preſented to the Lords for ſtopping or rectifying any Act or Decreet paſt in the Outer-houſe, untill the Party firſt make application to the Ordinary who heard and pronounced the ſame; and if he refuſe to hear the Party upon any new matter condeſcended on, or in caſe of doubtfulneſs, to report at leaſt upon conſignation of an Amaund: In that caſe, the Party may give in a Bill to the Lords, expreſſing his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to the Ordinar, and his refuſal to hear or report, as ſaid is, and expreſſing the ſpecial matter which he deſireth in the Proceſs, and no otherwayes.</p>
            <p n="16">16. To the effect, the Lords of Seſſion may be in better capacity to diſcuſs the Proceſſes which come before them, not being overburdened with ſmall and inconſiderable Cauſes, That all Cauſes, not exceeding the value of two hundred Merks <hi>Scots,</hi> be in the firſt inſtance carried on before the inferiour Judges; And that no Summons be raiſed upon Bill, or otherwayes for Cauſes of leſs importance, for which the Clerk of the Bills and Writers to the Signer are to be anſwerable at their peril; except there be ſuch reaſons condeſcended on in the Bill, as would be ſufficient to procure an Advocation of the Cauſe from the inferior Judge, in behalf of a Defender, and competent Inſtructions thereof; And that ſuch Bills do not paſs of courſe, but be ſpecially preſented and read to the Ordinary, and that the deliverance on the back thereof bear, <hi>Becauſe the Lords have found ſuficient ground, for which the Cauſe ought not in the firſt inſtance to be purſued before the inferiour Judge Ordinar, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lords:</hi> Excepting alſo, the Cauſes belonging to the Members of the Colledge of Juſtice, and except Sums due to Merchants, Cooks, Vintners and others in Burgh, for Furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38131:8"/>taken off from them, by ſuch as dwell not within the Shire where the Furniture was taken off.</p>
            <p n="17">17. That where Cauſes are begun before inferior Courts, no Advocation thereof ſhall be paſt, being of no greater im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance then as aforeſaid, otherwayes then is provided by the Act of Parliament; And that the Clerk of the Bills be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable therefore, not to preſent, paſs or write on any ſuch Bill at his peril.</p>
            <p n="18">18. That where Decreets are paſt before inferior Courts, and craved to be ſuſpended, if the reaſons proceed not on iniquity, but upon alledgiance, that the Decreet was in ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, ſo that the craver of the Suſpenſion hath never appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or hath not continued to defend while there was no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice done: Then and in that caſe, he ſhall be oblieged at the paſſing of the Bill of Suſpenſion, to conſign in the hands of the Clerk of the Bills, ſuch ſums for the expences of the Party, as the paſſer of the Bill ſhall appoint, according to the importance of the Cauſe and the diſtance of the Party, which ſhall be given up to the Charger, if the Suſpender hath not compeared, or continued to defend before the inferior Court, as ſaid is; and that immediately at the calling of the Cauſe to be diſcuſt, when the compearance in the Decreet may appear, unleſs the Suſpender improve the Executions of the Summons whereupon the Decreet did proceed.</p>
            <p n="19">19. That Decreets, <hi>in foro contradictorio,</hi> before the Lords of Seſſion be not again ſuſpended, upon reaſons competent to have been proponed, or which were repelled in the former De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet. And to the effect it may be known, with the leaſt expence, what Decreets are <hi>in foro,</hi> That the Keeper of the Minute-book make up a Book of the Decreets <hi>in foro,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the ſame ſhall each day be given in to him by the Clerks, expreſſing the names of all the Defenders for whom there is compearance; And that the Clerk of the Bills from time to time, call for and receive a double of the ſaid Minute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>book of Decreets <hi>in foro;</hi> And when any Bill of Suſpenſion is to be preſented by him, that at his peril he write on no Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion of any Decreet <hi>in foro,</hi> contained in the ſaid Book, untill it be preſented to the whole Lords in time of Seſſion, and to three met together in time of vacance, the deliverance bearing, that they were met together. And where there is once compearance for any Party and Defences proponed, the Decreet ſhall be holden as done <hi>in foro,</hi> and all the Diſpute proponed by the Advocats ſhall be inſert therein, albeit the Advocat thereafter paſt from his compearance; And that the firſt Proteſtation ſhall not be ſuſpended, but upon conſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thirty pounds, and the Suſpenſion thereof ſhall bear
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38131:8"/>that it is the ſecond Suſpenſion: And ſo forth, all the Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſions that ſhall be obtained thereafter, ſhall bear that the ſame is the third or fourth Suſpenſion; and that no Suſpenſion ſhall paſs of the ſecond Proteſtation, but in preſence of the whole Lords in time of Seſſion, and by three of the Lords met together in time of vacance, the deliverance bearing as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; and that the Clerk of the Bills write upon no Bill of Suſpenſion otherwayes, as he will be anſwerable at his peril; and that the ſecond and poſterior Proteſtations ſhall be inſert in the ſaid Book, with the ſaids Decreets <hi>in foro.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20. That where Proceſſes are keeped up un-returned by the Defenders Advocat, longer then ſix dayes after the out-giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof, which is the time allowed for ſeeing of Proceſſes, That upon complaint given in to the Lords thereanent, the Ordinary upon the Bills call the Advocat who keeps up the Proceſs, and fine him in three pounds <hi>Scots</hi> for ilk day he hath keeped up the ſame, from the time that the Proceſs was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired from the Advocat, or his principal Servant perſonally at the Advocats Chamber, by way of Inſtrument under a Nottars hand, unto the day that the complaint was given in, and ſix pounds for every day that the Proceſs ſhall be detained by him, after in-giving of the complaint: And that one of the Macers be ordered to exact the fine, under the pain of deprivation; and to that effect, that he be warranded to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the Advocat out of the Houſe, and not to ſuffer him to enter the Outer bar until he make payment; and that he return the money ſo exacted to the Ordinary upon the Bills, whereof the one half is to be put in the Poors Box, and the other half to be paid to the party purſuer, if he deſire the ſame, otherwayes, that the whole be put in the Box.</p>
            <p n="21">21. But where there are moe Defenders then one called in a Proceſs, and ſeveral Advocats compearing for them, That the Advocat who taketh up the Proceſs to ſee for the Party principally concerned, in whoſe houſe the ſame is appointed to be ſeen, ſhall be allowed only four dayes for ſeeing the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs; and in caſe he do not return the ſame within that time, that he incur the penalties contained in the former Article: And that after the Proceſs ſhall be returned, the ſame ſhall remain in the Clerks hands ſix dayes before it be called, dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which time, any Advocat compearing for any other of the Defenders, may ſee the Proceſs in the Clerks hands, and write thereupon for whom he compears, and ſubſcribe the ſame; and may alſo borrow the ſame up from the Clerk for the ſpace of twenty four hours, upon his Receipt and conſignation of an Amaund, according to the importance of the Cauſe: And in caſe he do not reproduce the Proceſs within the ſaid ſpace of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38131:9"/>twenty four hours, upon complaint made thereof, he is to loſe the Amaund, and to pay ſix pounds for ilk day he keeps the Proceſs after the ſaid ſpace of twenty four hours; and the like execution to be uſed therefore, as in the former caſe of the Defenders Advocats not returning Proceſſes given out to them by the purſuers Advocats. And likewiſe, if any Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocat, during the ſaid ſpace of ſix dayes, be deſirous to ſee the Proceſs for any other Party having intereſt, who was not called in the Proceſs, that upon production of the Parties in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in the Clerks hands, he be allowed to ſee in manner fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, he alwayes conſigning and ſubſcribing for whom he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears: And incaſe of failzie, to re-produce, being lyable as ſaid is; and that the Advocat ſhall not be heard when the Cauſe is called, if he hath neglected to ſee, in manner fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, whether he be compearing for any Party called in the Proceſs, or compearing for his Intereſt.</p>
            <p n="22">22. In reſpect it is a great obſtruction to the diſpatch of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, That when Cauſes are called, Defences ſometimes are proponed upon Writs, which being neither produced nor ſeen by the purſuers Advocats, all that is ordinarily done, is to ordain the Writs to be produced: Therefore, wherever the Defenders Advocat is to found any Defence upon Writ, that at the returning of the Proceſſe, he alſo produce there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Writs whereupon he intends to found any alledgeance, otherwiſe no reſpect is to be had to the alledgeance to be founded on theſe Writs which were in any of the Defenders Advocats hands, Or which, or any Coppy thereof were ſeen by the ſaids Advocats, which the Purſuers Advocats ſhall be obliedged to return within four dayes after they receive the ſame: Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes complaint may be made againſt them, as againſt Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders-Advocats, for keeping up of Proceſſes: And incaſe any other Writs come to their hands, after the returning of the Proceſs, upon which they will found; That in like manner they produce the ſame to the Purſuers-Advocats before calling of the Cauſe, under the ſame certification.</p>
            <p n="23">23. That the Suſpender at the out-giving of the Suſpenſion, produce therewith all his Verifications; And that at the calling of the Cauſe, if he have keeped up the Verifications, and offer then to produce the ſame, That the Ordinary ſhall give Decreet, becauſe the Reaſons is not verified conditionally; That if with the Verifications the Suſpender produce in the Clerks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hands twelve pound <hi>Scots,</hi> two parts thereof to be paid to the Charger, and the third part to the Poor, the ſame ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and the Parties heard thereupon, without Enrolling of new: And therefore the Ordinary ſhall mark upon the Cauſe, <hi>Decreet Conditional,</hi> to ſuch a day; And if betwixt and the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38131:9"/>ſaid day, obedience be not given, the Decreet is to be Extracted.</p>
            <p n="24">24. That the Suſpenders Advocat be not allowed to propone any new Reaſon of Suſpenſion at the Bar, which was neither ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled, nor contained in the eikit Reaſons of Suſpenſion given out to, and ſeen by the Chargers Advocats, unleſſe therewith they conſign in manner foreſaid.</p>
            <p n="25">25. That becauſe Proceſſes are very much lengthned, by the long running of ordinary and incident Diligences and Termes, for production in Reductions and Improbations: For remedy whereof in time coming, there ſhall only be two Diligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt Witneſſes, one by <hi>Horning,</hi> and another by <hi>Caption;</hi> And there ſhall be no Incident-diligence ſuſtained upon <hi>Acts,</hi> but where the fame is craved, and allowed at the pronouncing of the <hi>Act,</hi> and expreſſed therein; which ſhall proceed againſt the alledged Havers of the Writs, firſt by <hi>Horning,</hi> charging them to compear and produce upon Oath, and next by <hi>Caption</hi> incaſe they do not compear and depone: And that there be only one Term for Production in ſingle Reductions, and two in Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probations: And that the Clerks inſert no Reſervations in <hi>Acts</hi> for Production, but that all Exceptions competent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Production, be diſcuſs'd before aſſigning of Termes.</p>
            <p n="26">26. That no more Advocats be employed, or marked in any Cauſe for a Party, but only three in the Inner-Houſe, and three in the Outer-Houſe at moſt; And that only two be allowed in the Inner-Houſe to ſpeak one after another upon one ſide, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the other Party make an Anſwer: And that the Lord-Chancellor, or Preſident, keep the Advocats cloſs to the Point; And that no Advocat be allowed to ſpeak above half an hour together, at moſt at one time.</p>
            <p n="27">27. Seing there is great clamor and complaint of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant-allowance of late given to Advocats for Conſultations, far exceeding what was uſual in former times; That for reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy thereof, the allowance of Advocats in time coming, be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulat according to the quality of the perſons who employes them, and the Eminency of the Advocats employed, in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner following, <hi>viz.</hi> That for every Conſultation, pleading thereupon, and drawing Bills upon any Interloquitor there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anent altogether, there be given at moſt to any of theſe Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cats, who ordinarily plead in the Inner-Houſe, by Noblemen, eighteen pounds; By Knights and Barrons, fifteen pounds; By Gentlemen and chief Burgeſſes, twelve pounds; And by all the reſt of the People, nine pounds: And to the reſt of the Advocats by Noble-men, only twelve pounds; By Knights and Barrons, nine pounds; By Gentlemen and chief Burgeſſes, ſix pounds; And by all the reſt of the People, four pounds:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38131:10"/>And that nothing be allowed for drawing Informations to be given to the Lords after Diſput, but to one Advocat only; and that the allowance therefore, be only the half of what is allowed for the Conſultation.</p>
            <p n="28">28. That the Parties Purſuer and Defender, do give in with the Proceſs, a Declaration under their hands, bearing, That as they ſhall anſwer to God, they have not given, nor ſhall give any more to any one Advocat employed by them in that Proceſs, for every Conſultation comprehending as aforeſaid, then the foreſaid allowance; which Declaration is to be given in by the Defender at the return of the Proceſs, and by the Purſuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Proceſs be called; and incaſe of the Clients minority, his Tutors, or Curators; and incaſe of his abſence, or that he hath employed another to disburſe the mony for him; the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo employed, ſhall give in the foreſaid Declaration upon Oath, which ſhall bear, that he being the only Perſon employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to disburſe mony to Advocats in that Proceſs, he hath not given, nor ſhall give any more then as aforeſaid. And likewiſe, that all who are already admitted Advocats, before they be allowed to plead, ſhall give their Oaths that they ſhall alwayes obſerve the ſaids rates; and that no Advocats be admitted here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, till they give that Oath.</p>
            <p n="29">29. And becauſe by the Act of Parliament, one thouſand ſix hundred and twenty one, the rates of Writs are ordered con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to an Act of the Lords of Privy Council and Lords of Seſſion, in <hi>Anno,</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred and ſix, the effect whereof hath been fruſtrate, becauſe nothing thereby is provided to Clerks Servants: And in reſpect the rates of all things are much increaſed ſince that time, Therefore that the rates of the Clerks of Seſſion be as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi> That the ſame rates be obſerved which are contained in the ſaid Act of Parliament, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept as to Acts, Decreets, Proteſtations and Diligences, for which there ſhall be only paid to the Clerk and his Servants, three pounds <hi>Scots</hi> for each Sheet, written in the ſame manner as they are now accuſtomed, conform to a Pattern to be ſigned by this Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and keeped by the Lords of Seſſion: And that the Clerks or their Servants take no money for production of Writs, or giving up of the ſame again, minuting of Diſputes, or booking of Acts and Decreets, all which ſhall be paid by the ſaids Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts; but that there be allowed to them two Merks for taking a Parties Oath, and one Merk for every Witneſſes Depoſition, and thirty Shillings <hi>Scots</hi> for calling of every Act in preſence of the Ordinary. And that the Clerks or their Servants do not mark upon any Proceſs, Calling or Compearance, or the calling of any Act, but what was publickly done by a Macer, that the Advocats may have timeous notice to ſatisfie the concluſion of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38131:10"/>Acts; and that no Decreet be pronounced conditionally, but ſimply, according to the Act to be extracted twenty four hours after the ſame is read in the Minute book; and that every <hi>Sede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt</hi>-day the Minute-book be read out fully, that the Lieges be not delayed or neceſſitat to attend: And that the Clients ſhall, in the ſame manner as in relation to Advocats Allowance, give their Oaths, that they have keeped and ſhall keep the ſaids rates, which ſhall be contained in one paper, with their Declaration in relation to Advocats; and that the Clerks and their Servants give their Oaths, that they ſhall alwayes obſerve the ſaids Rules and Rates, and that no Clerk be admitted hereafter, till he give that Oath; excepting Acts and Decreets of contentious diſpute in preſence of the Lords, which are to be at the diſcretion of the Party, conform to the Act of Parliament.</p>
            <p n="30">30. And anent the Clerk of the Bills and his Servants, that the rates in the ſaid Act of Parliament, one thouſand ſix hundred and twenty one, be in all points obſerved, and alſo the rates for Allowance of Compriſings, contained in the Act of Parliament, one thouſand ſix hundred and ſixty one; with this alteration, That whereas that which is allowed by the ſaid Act, one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred and twenty one, for the Acts of Caution, with the relief which comprehends the Bills of Suſpenſion, is too low for the Clerk and his Servants, That there be allowed to the ſaid Clerk and his Servants therefore, three pounds and one merk <hi>Scots,</hi> and no more; and that the Clerk of the Bills and his Servants give their oaths, in the ſame manner as the Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cats and Clerks of Seſſion, that they ſhall obſerve the ſaids rates. And in caſe there be moe perſons contained in the ſaids Bills of Suſpenſion then one, that every ſuch perſon, except the chief perſon, ſhall pay ſix ſhillings eight pennies, until they come the length of ten perſons; and no allowance is to be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for any exceeding that number, nor for a Community more then the ſaid number of ten: And for Relaxations, ſix ſhillings eight pennies for every perſon more then one, untill they come to the number of ten perſons, and no more to be taken for any greater number or Community; and that this be in ſatisfaction of all that is to be given in that Office, both for Maſter and Servants.</p>
            <p n="31">31. In reſpect ſeveral perſons, being neither Advocats nor Advocats Servants, do take upon them, under the name of Agents, to medle and negotiate in Proceſſes, who are found to be of no uſe, but burdenſom to the Lieges; That hereafter all theſe Agents be debarred the Houſe, and not permitted to nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate in, or mannage Proceſſes; and recommends to the Lords of Seſſion to ſee the ſame punctually obſerved.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:38131:11"/>
            <head>Concerning the J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STICE-CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eing Cauſes Criminal are of the greateſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and may extend to the Lives and Liberties of any of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Subjects, and their Perſons and Fortunes: And ſeing the puniſhment of Crimes is of the greateſt conſequence for the ſafety and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Perſon and Authority, and the Peace and Quietneſs of the Kingdom; And therefore, Matters Criminal ought to be determined in the moſt ſolemn, exact and regular way, that the Loyal and Innocent may be in full ſecurity, and Offenders may be puniſhed either in the moſt publick places of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, or in the places where the Crimes have been committed, to terrifie others from the like: That whereas formerly Aſſeſſors from time to time were appointed to the Juſtice-General, in matters of importance, which being ambulatory, cannot be ſo convenient, as if all the Members of that Court were ſetled and choſen by His <hi>Majeſty</hi> of fit perſons, who might make it their work to make a juſt and conſtant procedure in Matters Criminal.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For that effect, that the Office of Deputes in the Juſtice-Court be ſuppreſs'd, and that five of the Lords of Seſſion be joyned to the Juſtice-General and Juſtice-Clerk, and all of them inveſted with the ſame and equal Power and Juriſdiction in all Criminal Cauſes; That the Juſtice-General being preſent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, in his abſence the Juſtice-Clerk, and in abſence of both, that theſe preſent elect one of their number to preſide, four of the whole number being alwayes the <hi>Quorum</hi> of that Court, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept at the Circuit-Courts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they be appointed to meet each Monday at nine of the clock in time of Seſſion, and oftner if buſineſs ſo require.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the perſons to paſs upon Aſſizes be liſted, and their Names and Deſignations inſert in an Roll to be ſigned by the ſaids Judges or their <hi>Quorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That for the ſplendour of that Court, all the Judges ſit in red Robes faced with white, that of the Juſtice-Generals be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lined with Ermine, for diſtinction from the reſt.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That once a year, in the Moneth of <hi>April</hi> or <hi>May,</hi> Circuit-Courts be keeped, two of their number appointed to go and keep Courts at <hi>Dumfries</hi> and <hi>Jedburgh,</hi> two at <hi>Stirling, Glaſgow</hi> and <hi>Air,</hi> and other two at the Towns of <hi>Perth, Aberdeen</hi> and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38131:11"/>
               <hi>Innerneſs,</hi> the Juſtice-General being alwayes ſuper-numerary in any of theſe Circuit-Courts.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That it be left and recommended to the Judges of that Court, to regulate the inferior Officers thereof, and order every other thing concerning the ſaid Court.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That a convenient Room be appointed for their meetings, Benches for the Judges, a place for the Juſtice-General, more eminent then the Seats of the other Judges; That the Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cats, Clerk, Aſſize and Pannels have diſtinct places appointed to them.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That the Clerk of the Court, nor no other perſon, be preſent with the Aſſize after they are incloſed.</p>
            <p n="9">9. That the Chancellor of the Aſſize mark what way every individual perſon who is upon the Aſſize ſhall vote, whether con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning or aſſoilzeing, and that on the ſame Paper wherein the Verdict of Aſſize is written, which after the pronouncing of the Verdict, is to be cloſed and ſealed with the Seals of the Court, of the Chancellour of the Aſſize, and of ſo many moe of that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as the Chancellor ſhall think fit, and never to be opened again, but by order of the Judges: With certification, if the Clerk who ſhall have the keeping of the ſaid Verdict, do make open the ſame without warrand, he ſhall be deprived of his Office, and otherwayes puniſhed as the Judges ſhall think fit.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That in all Criminal Purſutes, the Defender or his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocats be alwayes the laſt ſpeaker, except in caſes of Treaſon and Rebellion againſt the King.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That when any Criminal Libel or Summons of Exculpation are given and execute againſt any Party, that at the ſame time, Liſts of the Witneſſes to be adduced for proving of the ſaid Libel and Summons, and of the perſons who are to paſs upon the Inqueſt, be alſo given to them; to the effect, the Party may know what to object againſt the ſaids Witneſſes and Aſſizers, and may take forth Diligences for ſummoning of Witneſſes for proving of their objections, why any contained in the ſaids Liſts ſhould not be admitted to be a Witneſs, or upon the Aſſize.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>EDINBURGH,</hi> Printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to the King's moſt Excellent MAJESTY, 1670.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
